Bernard W. Reed Papers
Bernard W. Reed Papers
1915-1962
1935-1960
Reed, Bernard W. (Bernard Webster), 1916-1962.
3.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, research materials, course materials and a subject file. Reed's dissertation on the origins and history of the Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC) is well represented, and includes summaries of Proceedings of Annual Conventions, officer rosters, and transcripts of interviews with AUEC executives. There is also information on the Association of Urban Universities (AUU), the National University Extension Association (NUEA), and the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) as they relate to the AUEC. In addition, there are course materials from his tenure at the University of Chicago, many of which originated from the Industrial Relations Center. The subject file contains material related to adult education and evening colleges.
149539
Biographical History
Bernard W. Reed graduated from the University of Cincinnati in 1951, where he became Director of Information Programs (1952-1957), Assistant to the Dean, and assistant professor in the Evening College. He was affiliated with the adult education program of the University of Chicago (1958) and was Dean of the School of Continuing Education Professional Studies at Pratt Institute. He was the editor of Who's Who in the Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC), and from 1956-1962 he served as editor of the AUEC Newsletter. Dr. Reed died in 1962 shortly after completing his doctorate in adult education from the University of Chicago. His dissertation topic was the history of the AUEC.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bernard W. Reed Papers are divided into four groups: correspondence, dissertation materials, subject files, and course material. Reed's own classification scheme has been followed in arranging his papers. The inclusive dates of the collection are 1915-1962, but the bulk of the material is dated 1935-1960. The collection contains much primary material on the origins and history of the Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC) and some primary material from the period 1955-1962 on the National University Extension Association (NUEA)and the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA).
The Correspondence folder consists of typescript and carbon copies of incoming and outgoing letters, all concerning adult education research. Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Dissertation materials for the most part have been arranged chronologically by the approximate date of use and creation, not by the publication date of the materials he collected. Materials dealing with the method of writing a thesis are followed by his 1959 proposal, collected data, thesis chapters, and 1960 dissertation. However, from the time his proposal was written until the writing of his thesis began, it is not clear in what order he collected or worked on the material, and the organization is alphabetical for that period.
Material in this section consists primarily of typescript and handwritten notes as well as printed material concerning plans for his thesis and the history of AUEC -- its formation, organization and purposes. There are summaries of the Proceedings of the annual conventions, roster of officers, and portions of transcripts of interviews held with AUEC executives. (The phonotapes from which the transcripts were taken are found within the AUEC collection.) These interviews with founders and early members not only provide details of AUEC history, but include opinions of current adult education methods and organizations.
Also included in this category are three small notebooks, and dittoed and mimeographed materials concerning the activities of the Association of Urban Universities (AUU), NUEA, and CSLEA, especially as they relate to AUEC history.
Subject files contains an assortment of material, most of which deals with adult education and evening colleges. Subjects are arranged alphabetically. In this section, the listed dates are the actual dates of publication, not the dates Reed used the material. In two categories folder contents have been listed within the shelf list. There is an alphabetical list., by author, of thesis abstracts and proposals which Reed collected (including those of notable adult educators Malcolm S. Knowles, A.A. Liveright, and Roy J. Ingham); and a list of book reviews which follows Reed's subject classification scheme. Book reviews are handwritten, typescript, dittoed, mimeographed, carbon, and published material. Abstracts are either dittoed or mimeographed. The complete thesis included in this section is a typescript carbon copy.
Also included are lengthy typescript quotations from a number of books relating to adult education, arranged alphabetically by author. Other folders in this section deal with national and international adult education, the evening college and university extension services, and liberal education for adults. In these folders are special course description, pamphlets, addresses, clippings, and handwritten and typescript notes and quotations on the education of adults. Two remaining folders concern the relationship of education and leisure — mostly typed notes for a paper — and methods of studying one's community.
Course materials dates from Reed's years at the University of Chicago. Reed added substantially to the original course materials, continuing to use course structures as an organizational framework for carefully collected items on adult education topics such as teaching methods, group dynamics, and communication.
The papers in the collection consist of published reprints, news clippings, extensive (typewritten) excerpts, dittos, photocopies, and Reed's own notes. Two courses (Education 346 and 369) date from the years 1957 and 1958, but the collected materials extend up to 1961. Reed's notes clearly indicate that Education 346 was taught by Cyril Houle. Another source for course materials is the Industrial Relations Center (IRC) at the University of Chicago.
These materials originally were collected in large notebooks, divided into packets. This organization has been preserved, except that the notes, handouts, and bibliographies for each unit have been placed in the initial folder of that section. There are several breaks in the sequence of packets, as well as sections where no packet was indicated. In the latter instance, the material remains in its original position in the collection, without a packet number (or letter). Many of the materials are undated.
Separate, complete sets of course materials from the University of Chicago's Industrial Relations Center, Leadership and Human Relations Program (1957, 1958) are included: both the "Conference Leader's Guide" and student instruction books comprise ten booklet sets contained in looseleaf binders. Other materials from IRC courses can be found in folders at the end of the collection, along with other course materials from unidentified sources.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing. In particular, see also the following:
Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC) Records
Center for the Study cf Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) Records
George A. Parkinson Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Reed, Bernard W. (Bernard Webster), 1916-1962.; Association of University Evening Colleges (U.S.); Association of Urban Universities.; Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults.; University of Chicago, Industrial Relations Center.; National University Extension Association.; Adult education -- United States.; Educators -- United States.; Evening and continuation schools -- United States.; Correspondence.; Curricula.; Dissertations.; Drafts (documents); Lists.; Notebooks.; Syllabi.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Bernard W. Reed, 1966.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1955-1962 (Box 1)
- Dissertation material
  - Preparation of thesis, ca. 1959 (Box 1)
  - Proposal, 1959 (Box 1)
  - AUEC background
    - Early beginnings, ca. 1959 (Box 1)
    - Interviews, 1959-1960
      - Cochran, Harry A. (Box 1)
      - Hardy, Leslie P. (Box 1)
      - Holsapple, Cortell K. (Box 1)
      - Lang, Daniel A. (Box 1)
      - Love, Robert A. (Box 1)
      - Miller, Don S. (Box 1)
      - Mills, Henry C. (Box 1)
      - Neuffer, Frank R. (Box 1)
      - Parkinson, George A. (Box 1)
      - Waters, John A. (Box 1)
    - Notebooks, ca. 1959 (Box 1)
    - Organization and purposes, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Proceedings, 1939-1958; ca. 1959 (Box 1)
    - Rosters, 1957 (Box 1)
  - AAU proceedings, 1915-1939; ca. 1959 (Box 1)
  - CSLEA activities, undated (Box 1)
  - NUEA proceedings, 1915-1956; ca. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Thesis, 1959-1960
    - Chapters I-III (Box 2)
    - Chapters IV-V (Box 2)
  - Dissertation, 1960 (Box 2)
- Subject files
  - Adult education, 1953-1959 (Box 2)
  - Book reviews
    - Philosophy
      - Bryson, Lyman, Adult Education, 1936 (Box 2)
      - Bryson, Lyman, The Drive Toward Reason, 1954 (Box 2)
      - Great Britain Adult Education Committee, A Design for Democracy, 1919 (Box 2)
      - Hutchins, Robert M., Great Books: The Foundation of a Liberal Education, 1954 (Box 2)
      - Keppel, Frederick P., Education for Adults, 1926 (Box 2)
      - Kotinsky, Ruth, Adult Education and the Social Scene, 1933 (Box 2)
      - Lindeman, Edward C.,The Meaning of Adult Education, 1926 (Box 2)
      - Livingstone, Richard, The Future in Education, 1941 (Box 2)
      - Powell, John W., Learning Comes of Age, 1956 (Box 2)
      - Redfield, Robert, The Educational Experience, 1955 (Box 2)
    - History of adult education
      - Adams, Herbert B., Educational Extension in the United States, 1901 (Box 2)
      - Cartwright, Morse A., Ten Years of Adult Education, 1936 (Box 2)
      - Grattan, C. Hartley, In Quest of Knowledge, 1955 (Box 2)
      - Lund, Ragnar, ed., Scandinavian Adult Education, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Psychological development of adults
      - Havighurst, Robert J., Human Development and Education, 1953 (Box 2)
      - Overstreet, H.A., The Mature Mind, 1949 (Box 2)
      - Pressey, S.L., and Kuhlen, R.G., Psychological Development Through the Life Span, 1957 (Box 2)
      - Thorndike, E.R., Adult Interests, 1935 (Box 2)
      - Thorndike, E.R., Adult Learning, 1936 (Box 2)
    - Handbooks, directories, bibliographies, research
      - Debatin, Frank M., Administration of Adult Education, 1938 (Box 2)
      - Ely, Mary L., Adult Education in Action, 1936 (Box 2)
      - Ely, Mary L., Handbook of Adult Education in the United States, 1948 (Box 2)
      - Essert, Paul L., Creative Leadership of Adult Education, 1951 (Box 2)
      - Kempfer, Homer, Adult Education, 1955 (Box 2)
      - Knowles, Malcolm S., Informal Adult Education, 1951 (Box 2)
      - Sheats, Paul H., Jayne, Clarence D., Spence, Ralph B., Adult Education, the Community Approach, 1953 (Box 2)
      - Unesco, Adult Education: Current Trends and Practices, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Adult education agencies and institutions
      - Libraries
        - American Library Association, Public Library Service, 1956 (Box 2)
        - Berelson, Bernard, The Library's Public, 1949 (Box 2)
        - Chancellor, John, ed., Helping Adults to Learn, 1939 (Box 2)
        - Houle, Cyril O., Libraries in Adult and Fundamental Education, 1951 (Box 2)
        - Phinney, Eleanor, Library Adult Education in Action, 1956 (Box 2)
      - Public and community schools
        - Bogus, Jesse Parker, T he Community College, 1950 (Box 2)
        - Englehardt, N.L., Planning the Community School, 1940 (Box 2)
        - National Education Association, A Study of Urban Public School Adult Education Progress in the U.S., 1952 (Box 2)
        - Snow, Robert H., Community Adult Education, 1955 (Box 2)
      - Universities and colleges
        - Burns, Norman, The Community Responsibility of Institutions of Higher Learning, 1948 (Box 2)
        - Diekhoff, John S., The Domain of the Faculty, 1956 (Box 2)
        - Dyer, John P., Ivory Towers in the Market Place 1956 (Box 2)
        - Houle, Cyril O., The University, the City, and World Affairs, 1956 (Box 2)
        - Kelsey, Lincoln David, Cooperative Extension Work, 1955 (Box 2)
        - Lord, Russell, The Agrarian Revival, 1939 (Box 2)
        - Morton, John R., University Extension in the U.S., 1953 (Box 2)
        - Unesco, Universities in Adult Education, 1952 (Box 2)
      - Labor
        - Kerrison, Irvine L.H., Workers' Education at the University Level, 1951 (Box 2)
        - Mire, Joseph, Labor Education, 1956 (Box 2)
        - Stocks, Mary, The Workers' Educational Association, 1953 (Box 2)
      - Armed Forces
        - Houle, Cyril O., The Armed Services and Adult Education, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Program development
      - Program organization
        - Reeves, F.W., Adult Education, 1938 (Box 2)
        - Rural Social Systems and Adult Education, 1953 (Box 2)
        - Sorenson, Roy, and Dimock, Hedley S., Designing Education in Values, 1955 (Box 2)
      - Community study and community development
        - Lippitt, Ronald, Training in Community Relations, 1949 (Box 2)
        - Ogden, Jess, Small Communities in Action, 1946 (Box 2)
        - Reid, Jesse T., It Happened in Taos, 1946 (Box 2)
        - Ross, Murray G., Community Organization, 1955 (Box 2)
      - Method
        - Cartwright, Dorwin, Group Dynamics Research and Theory, 1956 (Box 2)
        - Chase, Stuart, Roads to Agreement, 1951 (Box 2)
        - Coyle, Grace L., Group Experience and Democratic Values, 1947 (Box 2)
        - Fansler, Thomas, Creative Power through Group Discussion, 1950 (Box 2)
        - Homans, George, The Human Group, 1950 (Box 2)
        - Liveright, A.A., Union Leadership Training, 1951 (Box 2)
        - Lowy, Louis, Adult Education and Group Work, 1955 (Box 2)
        - Mueller, Alfred, Principles and Methods in Adult Education, 1937 (Box 2)
        - National Society for the Study of Education, Adult Reading, 1956 (Box 2)
        - Schramm, Wilbur, Mass Communications, 1949 (Box 2)
        - Thelen, Herbert, Dynamics of Groups at Work, 1954 (Box 2)
      - Counseling
        - Klein, Paul, Counseling Techniques in Adult Education, 1946 (Box 2)
      - Programs for special groups
        - Cass, Angelica, Adult Elementary Education, 1956 (Box 2)
        - Donahue, Wilma C., ed., Education for Later Maturity, 1955 (Box 2)
      - Bibliographies, directories, research
        - Peals, Ralph A., The Literature of Adult Education, 1941 (Box 2)
        - National Education Association, Review of Educational Research, 1953 (Box 2)
        - Unesco, International Directory of Adult Education, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Community survey, ca. 1956 (Box 2)
  - Evening college and university extension, 1953-1962 (Box 2)
  - General-liberal-vocational education, 1954-1960 (Box 3)
  - International adult education, 1954-1960 (Box 3)
  - Leisure and education, ca. 1960 (Box 3)
  - Thesis abstracts and proposals, 1954-1960
    - Averill, Thomas, "An exploratory study of motives associated with self-education", 1959 (Box 3)
    - Brian, D. Garron, "Adult education in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints", ca.1959 (Box 3)
    - Campbell, Frank N., "A study of factors associated with community group activities in Wisconsin 4-H clubs", ca. 1959 (Box 3)
    - Chamberlain, Martin N., "The professional adult educator", ca. 1957 (Box 3)
    - Coughlan, Robert J., "Levels of management, corresponding work attitudes and the anticipatory socialization of vertically mobile individuals", 1960 (Box 3)
    - Crimi, James E., "Adult education curricula in the liberal arts colleges", 1954 (Box 3)
    - Halfter, Irma T., "The comparative academic achievement of women eighteen to twenty-five and women forty years of age and over", undated (Box 3)
    - Halfter, Irma T., "A contrast between the structure and functioning of undergraduate collegiate business education, day and evening divisions", undated (Box 3)
    - Hargett, Earl F., "A study of the relationship between self-education and intelligence", 1960 (Box 3)
    - Harrison, James W., "Criteria used in planning courses for adults by teachers, administrators, and students of evening colleges", 1954 (Box 3)
    - Harrison, James W., "Designing educational pro-grams for adults: a comparison of non-credit and credit courses in university evening colleges", 1957 (Box 3)
    - Ingham, Roy J., "A comparative study of two conceptions of adult education: community development and continuing education", ca. 1957 (Box 3)
    - Koch, W.H., "An investigation into concepts of citizenship: aspirations and concerns among selected groups of adult. agricultural migrant workers", 1960 (Box 3)
    - Knowles, Malcolm S., "The development of a coordinated adult education movement in the United States", undated (Box 3)
    - Larson, Melvin J., "Relationship of certain characteristics of church members to their financial support of denominational higher education", ca. 1956 (Box 3)
    - Lee, Robert, "The educational objective of the American public library: an historical study", 1960 (Box 3)
    - Lee, Robert, "The American Heritage project: an historical study", 1959 (Box 3)
    - Liveright, A.A., "Lay-leaders in adult education", 1954 (Box 3)
    - Mees, Carl F., "The historical development of the cooperative agricultural extension service in Cook County, Illinois", 1958 (Box 3)
    - Moorhead, Hugh S., "The Great Books Movement", 1960 (Box 3)
    - Orr, Betty, "The study of successful aging: the social role study", 1956 (Box 3)
    - Siegle, Peter E., "The social life of a Jewish community", undated (Box 3)
    - Soffen, Joseph, "Training of non-professionals in adult education", 1960 (Box 3)
    - Toone, Howard G., Jr., "A comparison of the operating principles of one hundred five university evening colleges", ca. 1957 (Box 3)
  - Thesis of Papanestor, William, A study of job satisfaction as related to need satisfaction, both on the job and off the job, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Quotations
    - Cantrell, Loula N., The growth and development of the Atlanta Division, University of Georgia, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Carnovsky, L., The Library in the Community, 1944 (Box 3)
    - Creese, James, The Extension of University Teaching, 1941 (Box 3)
    - Earnest, Ernest, Academic Procession, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Hamlin, Herbert M., The Public and Its Education, 1955 (Box 3)
    - Kolbe, Parke R., Urban Influences on Higher Education in England and the U.S., 1928 (Box 3)
    - McMahon, Ernest, lecture, ca. 1957 (Box 3)
    - Orr, Betty, dissertation, ca. 1957 (Box 3)
    - Rudy, S. Willis, The College of the City of New York, 1949 (Box 3)
    - Thwing, Charles F., A History of Higher Education in America, 1906 (Box 3)
    - Valentine, P.F., ed., Twentieth Century Education, 1946 (Box 3)
- Course material
  - Education 346, Adult Education, Packet 1
    - Syllabus, notes and bibliographies (Box 4)
    - General Definition (Box 4)
    - Overview (Box 4)
    - Andrew Hendrickson (1960 monograph) (Box 4)
  - Education 346, University Role, Packet 9
    - Notes and bibliography (Box 4)
    - University Training programs (Box 4)
    - University role: legislation (Box 4)
    - University role: addresses and speeches, 1958-1960 (Box 4)
    - University role: readings (Box 4)
    - University Afield 1926, readings (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Agricultural Extension, Packet 10
    - Notes and bibliographies (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Proprietary Schools, Packet 11
    - Notes, clippings, and bibliographies (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Vocational Rehabilitation, Packet 12
    - Bibliography (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Libraries, Packet 13
    - Readings (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Museums, Packet 14
    - Bibliography and general information (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Group Work Agencies, Packet 15
    - Notes and bibliography (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Labor Unions, Packet 16
    - Notes and bibliography (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Industry, Packet 17
    - Bibliography and general information (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Mass Media, Packet 18
    - Bibliography (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Adult Ed Agencies, Packet 19
    - Bibliography (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Family Life Education, Packet 20
    - Bibliography (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Community Development, Packet 21
    - Community Development: Bibliography (Box 4)
    - Community Development: Clippings, reprints, readings (Box 4)
  - Education 346, Adult Ed Organizations, Packet 22
    - Notes and bibliography (Box 4)
    - General information (Box 4)
  - Education 369, Teaching Methods, Packet G
    - Notes and bibliography (Box 5)
    - Notes and readings (Box 5)
    - Teacher Training: Standards (Box 5)
    - Teacher Training: Notes (Box 5)
  - Education 369, Adult Ed Materials, Packet H
    - Notes, bibliography, and syllabus (Box 5)
    - Canadian Film Board (Box 5)
    - Media (Box 5)
    - Readings and reprints (Box 5)
    - Other (Box 5)
  - Education 369, Adult Ed Programs [no packet letter]
    - Notes (Box 5)
    - Clippings and excerpts (Box 5)
    - Conferences and general info (Box 5)
    - Adult Ed Programming: Monographs (Box 5)
    - Adult Ed Programming: TV (Box 5)
  - Education 369, Adult Ed Financing, Packet K
    - Notes and bibliography (Box 5)
    - Excerpts and reprints (Box 5)
    - Reports and data (Box 5)
    - Examples (Box 5)
  - Education 369, Adult Ed Facilities [no packet letter]
    - Bibliography (Box 5)
    - Report and survey (Box 5)
  - Communications - general materials (Box 6)
  - IRC, communications booklets
    - Nos. 1-4 (Box 6)
    - Nos. 5-10 (Box 6)
  - Group Dynamics - general materials
    - Notes and bibliography (Box 6)
    - National Training Labs (Box 6)
    - Leadership Training (NAPSAE) (Box 6)
    - General information (Box 6)
  - IRC, Leadership training
    - Notes and materials (Box 6)
  - IRC, Issues and Ideas
    - 1956: Vol. 3, no. 11 (Box 6)
    - 1958: Vol. 5, nos. 7-11 (Box 6)
    - 1959: Vol. 6, nos. 1-5, 7-11 (Box 6)
    - 1960: Vol. 7, nos. 1, 2, 4, 5 (Box 6)
  - IRC, Leadership and Human Relations program
    - Conference leader's guide (Box 7)
    - Booklets, 1-10 (Box 7)